Guide to Sol Lutwak Papers RG.054
Poly Archives at the Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology, NYU Libraries
Sol Lutwak Papers
1939-1993
Poly Archives at the Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology, NYU Libraries
Lutwak, Sol (Sol Lutwak), 1928-2020
RG.054
6 Linear Feet (Four bankers boxes, one manuscript box, and one oversize box)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was donated to the Poly Archives by Sol Lutwak's daughter, Ellen Lutwak, and grandson, Benjamin Waldow, in September 2022.
Biographical / Historical
Sol Lutwak was born in Brooklyn, New York on March 27, 1928. He attended Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn where he was editor-in-chief of the Polytechnic Reporter and a member of the wrestling and tennis teams. In 1950, he graduated magna cum laude with a degree in aeronautical engineering. After graduation, Sol moved to California where he would go on to receive a Master's in Applied Mechanics from University of California, Los Angeles. He first worked at McCulloch Motors Corporation and then Hughes Aircraft Company, where he was an engineer for heavy-lift helicopters. He was one of the earliest employees at Ramo-Wooldridge Corporation in its division Space Technology Laboratory (STL) which later became TRW, Inc. Here he worked on satellite development through the American space shuttle and Apollo programs. While at TRW, Inc. he co-invented a structural computer program. Sol retired in 1992, and passed away on January 7, 2020.
Arrangement
This collection comprises six boxes donated by Sol Lutwak's daughter, Ellen Lutwak, and grandson, Benjamin Waldow. Original order was maintained when possible. The collection is arranged into these seven series: Series I: Brooklyn Poly, 1940-1950 Series II: Hughes Aircraft Company, 1952-1953 Series III: McCulloch Motors Corporation, 1949-1950 Series IV: National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA), 1960-1970 Series V: Other/Personal Materials, 1939-1993 Series VI: Space Technology Laboratories, 1957-1962 Series VII: TRW Inc., 1953-1992 and Series VIII: University of California, Los Angeles, 1953-1987.
Scope and Contents
The Sol Lutwak Papers contain documents from 1939 to 1993. These documents were assembled by Lutwak throughout his academic career at Brooklyn Polytechnic Institute and University of California, Los Angeles as well as his professional career at McCulloch Motors Corporation, Hughes Aircraft Company, and TRW, Inc. The collection contains professional documents such as reports and manuals, academic material such as exams and coursework, and personal materials such as books and memorabilia. The collection is six linear feet, located on bay 26, shelves 5B, 6B, and 7B.
Aerospace engineering; Systems engineering; TRW Inc.
- Series I: Brooklyn Poly, 1940-1950
  - Sub-series A: Associations, 1949
    - Tau Beta Pi Sigma Xi Certificate, 1949-05-13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Sub-series B: Commencement, 1948-1949
    - Brooklyn Poly 1949 Commencement Program, 1949-06-15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Graduation Portrait, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sub-series C: Coursework, Notes and Exams, 1947-1949
    - Airplane Design Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Airplane Structures Notebook, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Exam Books, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Airplane Structures Notes, Homework, Lab Reports, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Elements of Structures, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Theory of Elasticity by H.J. Reissner and V.L. Salerno, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Sub-series D: Handbooks and Manuals, 1940-1947
    - New Departure Hand Book, 1942-07 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Aerodynamics for Pilots by Bradley Jones, 1940-09-1943-04-14 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Airplane Design Eight Edition by K.D. Wood, 1947-09 (Box 1, Item 1)
    - Aircraft Mechanic's Pocket Manual by Joseph A. Ashkouti, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Sub-series E: Thesis, 1950
    - An Investigation of Approximate Methods of Solution for the Concentrated Load Problem by Sol Lutwak, 1950-06 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series II: Hughes Aircraft Company, 1952-1953
  - Basic Loads, XH-28 Helicopter, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - A Matrix Method for Determining the Spanwise Distribution of Normal Bending Moments on a Flexible Rotor Blade by Sol Lutwak, 1953-06-11 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series III: McCulloch Motors Corporation, 1949-1950
  - Basic Loads, 1949-10-18 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Loads Report Figures & Vu Graphs, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Stress Analysis of Collective & Diff. Coll. Pitch Control Systems by Sol Lutwak, 1950-10-09 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series IV: National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA), 1960-1970
  - Interlevel and Intralevel Correlations of Wind Components for Six Geographical Locations by William W. Vaughan, 1960-10 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - An Evaluation of Detail Wind Data as Measured by the FPS-16 Radar/Spherical Balloon Technique by James R. Scoggins, 1963-05 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Cape Canaveral Wind and Shear Data (1 Through 80km) for Use in Vehicle Design and Performance Studies by James R. Scoggins and William M. Vaughan, 1962-07 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Natural Environment Criteria for the NASA Space Shuttle Program by W.W. Vaughan, Title Page, 1970-02-09 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Series V: Other/Personal Materials, 1939-1993
  - Sub-series A: Books and Reference Materials, 1939-1993
    - Active Listening by Carl R. Rogers and Richard E. Farson, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Los Angeles Times Clippings: Southern California Defense Industry, 1993-12-05 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Applied Mechanics Dynamics by George W. Housner & Donald E. Hudson, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Physics by Erich Hausmann & Edgar P. Slack, 1939 (Box 1, Item 2)
    - Gamma Ray Observatory, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Writing Effective Reports and Memorandums, 1966-04-14 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Stardyne Structural Analysis System Brochure, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - System Management Organization, 1977-1991 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Employee Benefits, 1990 (Box 1, Item 3)
  - Sub-series B: Correspondence, 1987
    - Thank You from Daniel Goldin, 1987-09-23 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Sub-series C: Memorabilia, 1948-1993
    - Rocket Launch Photograph, undated (Box 6, Item 1)
    - Signed Retirement Poster, 1986 (Box 6, Item 2)
    - DSP Retirement Cartoon, undated (Box 6, Item 3)
    - Retirement Flyers, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Retirement Cartoons, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Pentagon Tour, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - TRW Rideshare Ruler, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1948-1993 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Retirement Card, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Kodachrome Slide, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - TRW Building Photos, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Bird Postcard, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series VI: Space Technology Laboratories, 1957-1962
  - Sub-series A: Certificates and Honors, 1960-1962
    - The Scientific Research Society of America Certificate, 1960-07-06 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Five-Year Recognition Luncheon Program, 1962-10-03 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Sub-series B: Notes and Data, 1957-1962
    - Article on Stiffened Pressurized Cylinders, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Wind Profile Data, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Item 1)
    - Problems Associated with Launch of Wind-Limited Space Boosters, 1962-04 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Statistical Wind Criteria Influence Coefficient Method, 1957-1960 (Box 2, Item 2)
    - Equivalent Load Per Inch on a Circular Shell Due to Applied Bending Moment, 1958-01-14 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Sub-series C: Reports, 1959-1961
    - Missile Structures, Dynamic Integrated Analysis, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Missile Structural Load by Nonstationary Statistical Methods, 1959-04-29 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Structural Design Criteria Transit/Courier by L.C. Killian, 1961-02 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Development of Design Criteria for Elastic Instability of Thin Shell Structures, 1959-01-01-1959-06-30 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Series VII: TRW Inc., 1953-1992
  - Sub-series A: Air Force Systems Division, 1959-1969
    - The Influence Coefficient Method for the Determination of Wind Shear Loads in the Preliminary Design of Booster Vehicles Part I & II, 1965-10 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - An Introduction to Booster Loads Analysis by S. Lutwak, 1969-12 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - The ARDC model atmosphere, 1959, 1959-08 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Improvement in the Influence Coefficient Method of Missile Design for Windshear Loads by Modification of the Wind Data Used, 1969-10 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Sub-series B: Conferences and Symposiums, 1961-1970
    - Launch Vehicles: Structures and Materials Conference, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Keyword Address by Richard V. Rhode to American Rocket Society, 1962-04-03 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - American Meteorological Society & American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics Conference Materials, 1966-03-28-1966-03-31 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Outline of "Loads Calculations for Ballistic Missiles" Talk, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - R.E. Bieber's Presentation at National Symposium on "Winds for Aerospace Vehicle Design", 1961-09-27-1961-09-28 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - AIAA/ASME 11th Structures, Structural Dynamics and Materials Conference Pamphlet, 1970-04-22-1970-04-24 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - National Symposium on Winds for Aerospace Vehicle Design Pamphlet, 1961-09-27-1961-09-28 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Sub-series C: Correspondence, 1965
    - Stress Concentrations Due to Holes in Thin Cylindrical Shells, 1965-08-19 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Sub-series D: Courses, Programs and Trainings, 1965-1987
    - Sparta Project Certificate, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - After Hours Program Certificates of Completion, 1969-1976 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - TRW Intergroup Project Management Course Presentation, 1987-04-16 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Continuous Process Improvement Bootcamp Achievement Award, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - How to Plan and Write Winning Proposals: Proposal Leadership Training Program, undated (Box 2, Item 3)
    - IBM 7090/7094 FRAN Framed Structure Analysis Program, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - A Guide to Fortran IV Programming by Daniel D. McCracken, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Computer Technology for Engineers I: Fortran Course Materials, 1969 (Box 2, Item 4)
  - Sub-series E: Drafts and Reports, 1959-1976
    - General Design Criteria Concepts for Space Vehicle Structure, 1969-03 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Minuteman Structural Design Criteria, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - In-Flight Wind Loads Structures Volume, 1968-01-19 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Aerodynamics, Vent Sizes, 1959-1963 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Structural Optimization: A Utilization of the TRW On-Line Computer by Joseph Hrzina, 1967-09-15 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Lehigh University Institute of Research Report by F. Beer and W. Lennox, 1964-03-15 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Model-35 Spacecraft Phase II Technical Advisor Briefing Series prepared by S. Lutwak, 1972-10-03 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - A Review of Space Vehicle Structural Design Problems During the Ascent Phase of Flight, 1968-03-18 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Rigid Body Bending Moment Program, 1959-1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Failure Investigation, 1976-02 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Sub-series F: Military Space Systems Division, 1971-1992
    - System Engineering Management Plan for the DSP-1 Spacecraft and Satellite Integration Segment, 1983-08-15 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - DSP Satellite Correspondence and News, 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Defense Support Program (DSP) Spacecraft 0023-0025, 1992-03-16 (Box 3, Item 1)
    - DSP-1, Satellites 23-25 Proposal Volume I Final Draft, 1992-05-15 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Reprinted Articles on DSP Satellites, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Proposal for DSP Satellites 0018-0022 (Multiyear Buy) Volume 1. Executive Summary, 1986-06-23 (Box 3, Item 2)
    - Proposal for DSP Satellites 0018-0022 (Multiyear Buy) Volume 2. Management, 1986-06-23 (Box 3, Item 3)
    - Proposal for DSP Satellites 0018-0022 (Multiyear Buy) Volume 6. Technical Considerations, 1986-06-23 (Box 3, Item 4)
    - DSP Executive Summary, 1992-05-15 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - DSP Communicator Volume 1, Number 2 Fall 1988 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - New Wind-Monitoring System Protects R&D Launches by William W. Vaughan, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - "Spy Photos from Space" Article Reprint, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - DSP Summary Briefing Originals, 1975-03-06 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - VUE History Data, 1983-1992 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Assorted Business Cards, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Photograph of Sol Lutwak, DSP Program Manager for Design and FAB, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Technical Committee on Structures, 1971-02 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Aviation Week & Space Technology w/ article on DSP Satellite, 1989-02-20 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Sub-series G: NASA Space Vehicle Design Criteria, 1961-1972
    - Terrestrial Environmental (Climatic) Criteria Guidelines for Use in Space Vehicle Development, 1969 Revision (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Effects of Structural Flexibility on Spacecraft Control Systems, 1968-12 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Volume III: Structures, Part B, Chapter 3, Section 9: Staging Loads, 1965-10-29 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Volume III, Part B, Chapter 3, Section 4: Propellant Slosh Loads, 1965-06-04 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Volume III, Part B, Chapter 3, Section 6: Wind and Maneuver Loads, 1965-10-22 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - In-Flight Winds (Terrestrial) Environmental Volume, 1968-05-15 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Volume III, Part B, Chapter 1, Section 2: Panel Flutter, 1964-07 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Volume III, Part B, Chapter 3, Section 1: Buffeting, 1964-05-01 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Local Steady Aerodynamic Loads During Launch and Exit (copy), 1965-05 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Volume III, Part D, Chapter 3, Section 1: Flight-Loads Measurements During Launch and Exit (copy), 1965 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Structural Design Criteria Applicable to a Space Shuttle, 1972-03 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Author's Guide for the Preparation of Space Vehicle Design Criteria Monographs in Structures, 1967-10 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Collection of Specs for Factors of Safety, 1961-1965 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Ground Winds - Environmental Volume, 1969-08-22 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Natural Environment Criteria for NASA Space Shuttle Program by William W. Vaughan, 1968-12 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - User's Manual - Rigid Body Loads Program, 1968-05-13 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Sub-series H: Reference Materials, 1953-1969
    - Structure Papers, 1963-1965 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Letter Symbols for Quantities Used in Mechanics of Solids, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - More Clippings: Space Flight, 1953-1969 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - NATO III D Communications Satellites by Ford Aerospace and Communications Corporation, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Articles from Aerospace Engineering, 1959-1962 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Articles from Space/Aeronautics, 1961-1967 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Articles from Product Engineering, 1965-1969 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Cannon Launched Rocket, 1964-07-09 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Articles from Aeronautical Engineering Review, 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Aircraft and Missiles Manufacturing, 1959-06 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Space Age News, 1965-02 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Articles from Aviation Week & Space Technology, 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - AIAA Sounding Board - Astronautics & Aeronautics, 1966-08 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Propeller Symbols, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Minimum Weight Analysis Based on Structural Reliability, 1960-09 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - "Quality Control, Testing Seen Key to Future Aeronautical Advances" by John F. Judge, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Articles from Engineering Opportunities, 1966-10 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Chapters 8-10 from "Manned Spacecraft: Engineering Design and Operation", 1965 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Articles from Machine Design, 1959-07-09 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Articles from Western Aerospace, 1964-03 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - 47 Ways to Shape and Form Materials from Materials Engineering, 1968-09 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Articles from Astronautics and Aerospace Engineering, 1963-04 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - TRW Space Log Fall 1965 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - TRW Space Log Spring 1967 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Typical Flowdown-Contractual Requirements to Hardware, undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Sub-series I: Spacecraft Engineering Division, undated
    - Spacecraft Development Program, undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Sub-series J: Structures Oriented Exchange, 1968-1970
    - An Introduction to STORE, 1968-12 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - ONR Structural Computer Programs Project (STORE) Final Report, 1969-05-05 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Introduction to Stru-Pack Service, undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Instructions for Use of the Structures Oriented Exchange (STORE), 1968-11 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - STRU-PAK Booklet, undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - STRU-PAK & MCAUTO, undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - STRU-PAK Correspondence, Data and Access Proposal, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Item 1)
    - STRU-PAK Instruction Guides Group I, 1970 (Box 4, Item 2)
    - STRU-PAK Instruction Guides Group II, 1970-01 (Box 4, Item 3)
- Series VIII: University of California, Los Angeles, 1953-1987
  - Sub-series A: Correspondence, 1987
    - UCLA Recommendation Letter, 1987-01-07 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Sub-series B: Coursework, Notes and Exams, 1953-1958
    - Rigid Body Dynamics, 1953-1957 (Box 4, Item 4)
    - Materials List, undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - UCLA Correspondence Records, Course List, Resume & List of Reports, 1957-06 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Grade Reports, 1958-01 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Financial Function Practice, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Sub-series C: Thesis, 1960-05
    - The Buckling of Conical Shells Under Axial Compression, 1960-05 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Series IX: Accretions, 2023
  - Accretions, 2023: Sol Lutwak stationary, TWC Space Log Winter 1968-69, circa 1968 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Accretions, 2023: Sol Lutwak stationary, Aeronautical Vest-Pocket Handbook, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Accretions, 2023: Dept. of Defense Security Questionnaire, "The Social Inadequacies of the Engineer", 1979-08-16 (Box 7, Folder 3)